All right.
So hi, everyone.
We're going to get started.
So for today's lecture
for CS25, very pleasure
to have Denny Zhao from
Google DeepMind here
to give a talk on large
language model reasoning.
And so Denny founded
the reasoning team
at Google Brain, which is
now part of Google DeepMind.
His group is renowned for
pioneering chain-of-thought
prompting and
self-consistency, as well as
developing the
mathematical foundations
of in-context learning and
chain-of-thought reasoning.
His team also created
core capabilities
that power Gemini's
reasoning capabilities.
Further, Denny
co-founded the conference
on language modeling, or COMM,
and served as general chair
for the 2024 conference.
So yeah, I'll let Denny
take it from here.
[APPLAUSE]
I'm glad to see many of
you guys have already
believed LLMs can reason.
Actually, you may wonder what
my answer for this question.
Yeah.
To me, actually, I don't know.
That really depends on the
definition of reasoning.
So for my talk today, I will
have a very specific definition
about reasoning.
So I know there's many debates
about if LLM's can reason.
I never join those
debates because
without a definition
on reasoning,
I have no idea
about those things.
But for LLM reasoning,
we particularly
mean that intermediate tokens
between input and output
that are called reasoning
are our intermediate steps.
So this idea actually
is not very new.
Even in 2017, DeepMind
already published a paper,
How to use Intermediate
Tokens to Solve Math Problems.
So at that time, I think the
community were quite hyped
about AlphaGo, Alphazero.
But this paper is a really
groundbreaking paper.
If you haven't read
that paper before,
I strongly encourage you
to look at that paper.
They introduced natural
language to solve math problems.
However, in the
literature at that time,
I think everyone else just used
the symbolic approach or search.
So actually, this
idea actually is also
very common for neural
symbolic literature.
In neurosymbolic
literature, actually, it's
very common to use intermediate
process to solve some reasoning
problems.
Here's an example about
how to use LLM reasoning.
When I founded the original
team in Google Brain,
I created this task.
So it's called last
letter concatenation.
I use this task as a
motivating example.
At that time, one could
use transformer models
to solve this task.
So what's the output
when concatenating
the last letter of each word
of artificial intelligence?
So if there is no reasoning
process, you will say,
OK, the answer is LE.
If there is a reasoning process,
the model would output, say--
the last letter of
artificial is L.
The last letter of intelligence
is E. Concatenating L and E
leads to LE, or
something like that.
So the highlighted text
here is called reasoning.
That's what I particularly
mean here about reasoning.
So if you are familiar
with program synthesis
or neural symbolic
reasoning, you
wouldn't be surprised
about this task design.
Of course, you can imagine
that I tried other options.
For example, I didn't
see the first letter.
The reason is that I
tried first letter,
and all language models
can solve that problem
quite well because there are
so many initiatives on the web,
and the model has
already learned how
to concatenate first letters.
Then I switched to last letters
and tthe old models failed.
I know many people say, oh
yeah, this is so natural, right?
We need intermediate
steps, just like humans.
I know in the
current days, you may
see LLMs are very
similar to humans.
But for us as researchers, we
should always keep in mind,
LLMs are just
probability models.
They are not humans.
And if you always
keep this in mind,
it will be better
for you to understand
a lot of new techniques.
So why intermediate tokens
or reasoning matters?
OK.
We have theoretical
work, actually
collaborated with
Professor Tuyima
in Stanford and his students.
So for any problems solvable
by Boolean circuits of size t,
constant-size
transformers can solve it
by generating O(T)
intermediate tokens.
This is a very powerful result.
So the size here means
the number of logic gates.
So for example, if you
use a GPU clusters,
that would be tens of
millions case, right?
Even billions, trillions.
Yeah.
If we directly generate
the final answers,
either we require a huge
depth or cannot solve at all.
That's how we
understand reasoning
from a theoretical perspective.
In the latter of this
lecture, I will come back
to this theoretical argument.
There is a common belief
about LLM reasoning.
And pre-trained LLMs cannot
reason without further prompting
engineering like code
prompting or fine tuning.
In the current days, everyone
talks about AI fine tuning,
right?
Is that true?
Do everyone agree with that?
You agree with that?
OK.
So I believe it's wrong.
Yeah.
It's very wrong.
So pre-trained LLMs
are ready to reason,
and all we need is a decoding.
Just about the decoding process.
Yeah.
No matter how fine
those techniques looks
like in [INAUDIBLE].
So here is an example here.
If I have three apples, my dad
has two more apples than me,
how many apples do
we have in total?
If you have any pre-trained
models like Lama,
DeepSeek or [INAUDIBLE]
or something--
I didn't try those models.
OK.
If you have any
pre-trained models,
you can type this question
in the pre-trained model
and see what happens.
Probably it's very likely you
see answer like five apples.
Of course, the
answer is wrong here.
This is called a
gradient decoding.
You will say, OK,
yeah, you're right.
For pre-trained models,
there is no reasoning, right?
The problem is about decoding
because the way you also decode
gradient decoding by default.
If you look at the
second candidate--
if you look at the--
because you have big
vocabulary size, right?
And you can look at
the second candidate--
a second candidate
for the first token.
And probably we start from
I and we see what happened.
We just then continue
the decoding process.
We see, OK, I have three
apples and then my dad
has two more apples than me.
So he has five apples
and 3 plus 5 equal to 8.
It's perfect, right?
We just need to look
for more candidates.
That's amazing.
And there's another choice.
And the third candidate
for the first token is we.
We see what happens here.
We have eight apples in total.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's it.
Somehow it's always cracked.
And [INAUDIBLE] probably
from the fourth candidate
would be you.
We will continue decoding.
We'll see what
happened here again.
Yeah.
You can clearly see a chain
of thought in this response.
And the final answer is correct.
And this is the fifth
candidate for the first token.
And the answer is 5.
It's wrong.
OK.
Yeah.
You can see that actually,
the reasoning part is already
in the output space.
And in particular here,
for the second response
and the fourth
first response, they
are based on
chain-of-thought reasoning.
The problem is how to select
the best response, right?
If you just look at
the examples here,
you may see, OK, we
can by output lengths.
If the model has some
thinking, the output length
will be longer because it
contains reasoning tokens.
And actually we have a better
idea to select the response
and by its answer confidence.
Confidence means because
the model is just
a probabilistic model, we
can look the probability
of the token in prediction.
A very interesting thing is
that for the response with chain
of reasoning, the answer token
has way higher confidence.
For this example,
actually for the token 8,
the model's confidence
is nearly 98%.
That's huge because we
have huge vocabulary size.
So usually for each token
the probability is nearly 0.
So this process is called a
chain-of-thought decoding.
So basically it
consists of two steps.
Step 1, is we just go
beyond greedy decoding
by checking more
generation candidates.
And in the second
step, we choose
candidates which
have the highest
confidence on the final answer.
And chain-of-thought decoding
is a very simple approach.
But still it needs
some programming work.
And I heard in the countries
and the people just
want to use natural language.
No one read the code.
Of course, you guys
are exceptional.
And we have to say, OK, can
we reshape the model's output
distribution so that thoughtful
responses naturally rank first?
If the chain-of-thought
response is
ranked first and then
the gradient decoding
can naturally find it.
So now we can look at the
chain-of-thought prompting.
If you know
chain-of-thought prompting,
now you can see why it works.
Chain-of-thought prompting
is a very simple approach.
So given this problem,
and you probably
use another similar
problems as an example,
and put that before
your question.
And then the model
will magically
follow the reasoning
style and generate a step
by step solution.
Yeah, now you can see that why
chain-of-thought prompting works
because it changes the
output distribution to push
the original chain-of-thought
solutions in the output space
to the top position.
Even there is a simple
approach is called
let's think step by step.
There's another amazing
work in the reasoning.
When that paper came out
I thought it was a joke.
How possible?
Yeah.
And at that time,
the Google Brain team
built a model called PaLM.
And I tried lessons that let's
step by step in our PaLM model
because, of course, I
know how PaLM was built.
It's definitely not related
to this magic trick.
And then I found
it works on PaLM.
I was so shocked.
So this paper really inspired
me a lot on reasoning research.
Those prompt approach are really
simple and prompting really
works.
But what I see there's
also some pitfalls.
So like CoT prompting it
needs task-specific examples.
To me, I don't feel
comfortable about that.
If I have questions
to ask someone,
if I know similar problems,
then I can solve it by myself.
Why should I ask other people?
And for the other approach is
called let's think step by step
is generic.
You don't have to
find similar examples.
You just say let's
think step by step.
And then the magic
will come out.
Unfortunately, it performs much
worse than a few shot prompting.
And, yeah, I just
mentioned that.
OK, yeah, both
approach looks weired.
Even for let's think step
by step is also weired.
If I ask someone
a question, then I
have to follow with
let's think step by step.
Otherwise, they
couldn't think anymore.
That's not expected.
So how to fix it.
So these are popular approach
called supervised fine tuning.
So for this approach, the
idea actually is very simple.
We can collect a set of problems
and the step-by-step solutions
from human annotators.
And then we maximize the
likelihood of human solutions.
Maximum likelihood
actually for LLMs training
pretty now token just
maximize likelihood.
Yeah.
And after that we can
apply the model everywhere.
So I listed DeepMind
paper in 2017.
I mentioned that paper
at the very beginning.
Yeah, they exactly did
something like that.
They collected a set of
math word problems and also
human annotated
step-by-step solutions.
And then they train a
sequence to sequence model
to solve math problems.
In 2021 an OpenAI
actually further extended
that approach, built
a much larger data set
called GSM8K grade
school math problems,
and then they used those data
set to fine tune GPT-3 models.
So here let me give an
example of how it works.
You can just put a problem here.
For example, at the
beginning I said, OK, we
can do last letter
concatenation.
And you can put
this example here.
The problem and the answer.
And the other one is
the semantic problem.
How many apples
you can put there.
And then use that as a training
data to fine-tune your model.
And then you can test the
model with a new question.
So how many r's in strawberry?
Probably you know
why I particularly
chose this problem here.
Because in social
media, many people
believe that it's a good
question to test if AGI has come
or not.
Yeah.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, and SFT is really
a generic approach.
Once you train a model,
you can apply it anywhere.
And if that can solve
reasoning my talk is done here.
We don't have to talk more.
Just collect more examples
from those brilliant minds
in Stanford.
We can train a
model and it's done.
But actually it doesn't
generalize well.
And we realize this issue
in 2021 in the summer.
We found it didn't
work well on reasoning.
What we could do?
Scaling, scaling, scaling to
get more data to train the model
and see how it works.
There a lesson here,
don't scale blindly.
Once the paradigm is wrong,
no matter how you scale,
it doesn't work.
So how to fix the
generalization failure from SFT?
Let's look at SFT
procedure here.
There are two steps.
So where is the mistake?
The mistake part
actually "from human."
If you do not know that
before, you will be surprised.
If a human entities are
wrong and the whole scale
AI can make money.
And actually one of my team
members invented a fine-tuning,
actually, when he told me--
and the response
generated by machines
could even better for
training than human data.
I was really surprised
at the very beginning.
Yeah.
So first attempt is
called self-improve.
Yeah, exactly just change that.
OK, instead of collecting
data from humans,
we can just let the
model generate data.
So collect a set of problems
and also then let your model
generates step-by-step
solutions.
And then again, maximize the
likelihood of correct answers.
Like math problems, you
may know the final answer.
You know the ground
truth answer,
but you don't have
step-by-step solutions.
OK, let model generates
And then you can use
it to answer to decide
which response to be used.
If the answer is correct from
the solution, then choose that.
Otherwise, reject.
It's called reject sampling.
And then you can use this data
set to fine-tune your model,
exactly as you have
done in the SFT.
The only difference is the
data is from the model.
It's not from humans.
And this approach actually
was proposed by Eric and Tony
and also Noah.
The paper is called Star.
Yeah, the Star paper,
it's really amazing paper.
So actually, in the Star paper,
when they proposed the approach,
they consider to use that
to save cost, labeling cost,
because human labeling
are really expensive.
But in the current days,
we understand this approach
from different perspective.
Once the response are
generated, or training data
generated by the model and
the model can be self-improve.
And after the model improved
and we collect data again,
that means we can repeat
this process, repeat.
And then this approach is then
just the same as the fine-tuning
approach, in [INAUDIBLE].
I put a paper here, and I think
it's a paper by researchers
in ByteDance.
Published in January
2024, I think
this is the earliest
academia publication I have
noticed about AI fine-tuning.
Even the paper title
is called Reasoning
with Reinforced Fine-Tuning.
Yeah.
I think after
[INAUDIBLE] got popular
and then everyone began
to realize RL fine-tuning
in the public.
Yeah.
I believe multiple
institutions independently
discovered this idea.
This is such a simple idea.
But it works really well.
Of course, yes, after seeing
this RL fine-tuning process,
and we need verifier
in this training loop,
the verifier can tell us which
response is correct because we
know the final answer.
We just need to
use that to select
the step-by-step reasoning path.
So a reliable verifier
is the most crucial in RL
fine-tuning, know
there are algorithms.
In the current
days, so many people
talk about different
algorithms and so
many tons of variants
of PPO are reinforced.
If anyone found those
some algorithms are
significantly better than
another one, please let me know.
Probably I missed something.
Yeah, I really like what
Rich Sutton said here.
"Verification, the key to AI."
It's an article title
by Rich Sutton in 2001.
Now a very interesting question
is, why generated from the model
instead of from humans?
That's a really
interesting question.
It's not about saving cost.
It's about performance.
Does anyone have an idea here?
Yeah.
Is it consistency?
In data cloud structure
versus humans,
there's more variation
in how different
people might approach problems?
About consistency, OK.
Yeah?
The solution is
closer to [INAUDIBLE].
The stability--
[INAUDIBLE] model is closer
to what you need to train.
It's easier to train the model.
Yeah, excellent, yeah.
Yeah.
Thanks.
So yeah, this is related
to first principle
in machine learning, directly
optimize what we want.
I don't know if anyone still
remember some machine learning
stuff here.
Of course, you guys should
remember that, yeah.
So if we want to build a
model for reasoning, or just
in general about generating
something interesting,
we need to optimize the metrics
of measuring generation quality.
Those metrics could be
very, very different.
For example, if we're
solving math problems,
we would care about
the correctness--
the answer is correct or not.
If for machine
translation, you would
optimize BLEU score,
or just about a metric
to measure the quality
of generations.
Once you have a
metric, all we need
is to compute gradients of the
metric and do back propagation.
Yeah.
So mathematically, we
can write this formula.
We need a function r
to measure the response
quality given the
problem and also
your model parameter, theta.
Yeah.
Of course, you can
see r is a reward
or r is your
classification accuracy
or r is your BLEU score.
Well, no matter.
You can define any r you want.
That's your target.
And then compute the gradient.
Assess the model is
a previous model.
We need to maximize the
expected value of the metric.
So how to do it?
We need sampling to
compute expectation.
That's why you get
a policy gradient.
Yeah.
That's how it works.
If you understand all the
mathematical principle here,
there is no magic.
I know some people would
like to talk about something
in a more magical way.
For example, how to
incentivize your model to sync,
incentivize your
model to reason?
I don't use those words.
I just use a standard
machine learning words.
Define your metric,
compute gradient,
and do backpropagation.
That's all.
Yeah.
Of course, yeah.
Once you find your
paradigm works well,
we need to scale your approach.
Not a problem.
It's, what to scale?
And the interesting is that
for this RL fine-tuning
approach we scale
the output length
or scale the length of CoT.
And you probably also
scale the model depth.
Because from our
theoretical analysis,
once, as long as your
CoT is long enough,
the model can solve nearly
every computable problems.
That's amazing.
You don't have to
scale your model size.
You just need a minimum
constant-size transform models,
and that's fine.
So actually, if you look at
literature, and people realized
RL fine-tuning is better than
HFT in the very early days,
but it's harder to notice that
we need to scale the CoT length.
That's even more
non-trivial to realize.
Yeah.
I would like to mention the
beauty of LLM reasoning.
Human-like reasoning
process emerged
from token-to-token
prediction, rather
than relying on exhaustive
search as in classical AI.
Yeah.
I also have fund
quote here by Kasparov
after losing to
Deep Blue in 1997.
And he said, "Deep Blue was
only intelligent the way
your programmable alarm
clock is intelligent."
Actually, I agree with him.
But LLM reasoning is different.
We don't do any explicit
search, and the search
is irrelevant here.
And before my talk,
in the hallway
she quoted my tweet about
search is irrelevant.
And wow, I said, I'm
happy to know that.
Actually, I used the quote
to see search is useful.
Actually, I want to
give an example here
about why is LLM reasoning is
so different from classical AI
here.
In December 2024,
and Google released
a model called Gemini 2.0.
thinking mode.
Of course, 2.5 pro is
much more powerful.
I use that model is
for particular reason.
So in December 2024,
after model release,
I tried a math problem just
to ensure this problem is not
in our training set.
And because I use number
2025 for the next year--
now for this year--
using the numbers from
1 to 10 to make 2025
and using each number once,
and the primary operations
plus and the multiplication.
Of course, one can
write a Python program
to do exhaustive search
and get the results.
Let's look at the thinking
process on the right panel
generated from the model.
Actually, for Gemini models, you
can check the thinking process,
as it's very
interesting to look at.
Let's see how the
model did the thinking.
It's not by search.
You can see that, at the very
beginning, the model said,
OK, this is a
relatively large number.
Suggesting multiplication
will be heavily involved.
That's just like
a human thinking.
And well, even I see
it's worth noting
that 2025 is a 45 squared--
45 times 45.
Actually, when I
made this question,
even I didn't realize
this huge hint here.
Let's see.
So the target is
large, and it started
thinking about how to get
large intermediate products,
use multiplication
and see blah, blah.
And that's "M" for products that
get us closer to the square root
of 2024, which is 45.
You see that?
And after, actually,
I made a cutoff here.
The thinking is very, very long.
That's why we need a long
CoT in the RL fine-tuning.
And you can find the answer.
After thinking, the model
showed the final answer.
They exactly follow
the thinking process.
And see that's the
breakdown of it.
First part, 10 times 4 plus 5
equal to 40, plus 5 equal 45.
And the second part is also,
again, 45, and then 45 times
45 to get 2025.
That's amazing.
We don't need any search.
I don't know if anyone
read another paper related
to chain-of-thought prompting.
It's called a
train-of-thought prompting.
Anyone read that paper?
Yes.
Great.
Yeah.
In that paper, actually, there's
a very interesting example
is Game 24.
This problem is way
harder than Game 24.
In train-of-thought
prompting, they
combine search with
prompting to solve Game 24.
But now you don't
need that at all.
The model can solved Game
24 just by natural language.
See that is how RL
fine-tuning is so powerful.
It's amazing.
And again, I would like
to cite Rich Sutton here
you see in The Bitter Lesson.
The core idea here, "building
in our discoveries only makes it
harder to see how the
discovery process can be done."
Yeah, I think Rich Sutton
wrote The Bitter Lesson
after he joined Google
DeepMind, and he saw the success
of AlphaGo and AlphaZero.
And he said, OK, only two
processes are really scalable.
One is learning.
Data is a search.
But here.
I would like to see--
I only emphasize one thing.
Learning is scalable.
We just need learning.
Yeah.
For RL fine-tuning,
yeah, the big advantage
is that it generalizes
so well for automatically
verifiable tasks because we
need to verify in the loop.
There's no way put a
human in the loop there.
And of course, not all tasks
are automatically verifiable.
Can anyone give example
of non-verifiable tasks?
Yeah?
Creative writing.
Mm?
Yes, creative writing.
Yeah, great example.
Yeah.
That's the big restrictions for
RL fine-tuning at this point.
And also, many people are
really interested in creating
RL algorithms to
improve the approach.
I really want to see--
we spend more time
to think about how
to solve those
non-verifiable tasks,
for real problems
that actually really
are non-verifiable like
creative writing, even coding.
I know.
Si people say, OK,
coding problem will
be solved by AI in a few years.
And I think it will be very
challenging to be solved.
I know actually for--
they were talking
about a programming,
they only talk about
competitive programming.
Competitive programming is not
like our daily programming work.
So we write code.
We care about your
design, your readability,
how to collaborate
with other people,
not just give a final answer.
Yeah.
I have a talked about
all the other ideas.
Actually, at the very beginning,
I talked about CoT decoding.
Actually, the written part is
already in the output space,
and all we need to
do is about decoding
to reshape the output
distribution such
that CoT decoding found it.
And then I talked about
chain-of-thought prompting
or lessons by step, which can
reshape the output distribution.
And then SFT and
then RL fine-tuning.
RL fine-tuning is so
powerful, but we still
have a chance to improve
those process is-- basically,
I want to talk
about two key ideas.
One is aggregation.
The other is about retrieval.
And we have seen that LLM
reasoning is really powerful.
But any decoding issue in the
paradigm of generating reasoning
tokens and then final
answers, it seems so natural--
giving a problem, and generating
intermediate tokens, and then
final answer.
Does anyone see any
problem in this process?
Any problem?
Yeah?
Is the design of the model?
The model is just designed
to predict the next token.
The challenge is the way
it predicts the next stop.
That's what creates a situation
where the outcome is not
being aligned to the
expected outcome.
Yeah, great, yeah.
The model is originally
designed just
for pretty narrative
[INAUDIBLE].
So, yeah, thanks.
So yeah, we need to always
keep in mind here that LLMs
are probabilistic models.
They are not humans.
What does that mean
mathematically?
Let's think about what LLM does
in decoding-- give the problem,
and the generative reasoning,
and then final answer,
and then the response
found by greedy decoding.
What does greedy decoding mean?
arg max, the probability.
However, for us, we need to
are max the final answer,
choose the answer with
the maximal probability.
Choose the most
confident answer.
So they are not aligned.
It's such a simple high-school
conditional probability math
here, but it's
really useful for us
to understand the
decoding process.
And let's fix it.
We just need a one
step further OK.
If we generate
reasoning paths, we
should sum over
all reasoning paths
to find the probability
of the final answer.
In terms of machine
learning, it's
called marginalization,
to sum over all,
because all the reasoning
paths actually essentially
are just latent variables.
And of course, if you first
start machine learning
and then actually you
know this, the sum
can be computed by sampling.
And then once you got this
idea, and you say, OK,
that's exactly the
motivation underlying
or another popular approach
is called self-consistency.
So generate multiple
responses by randomly sampling
and then choose the answer
that appears most frequently.
So let me show a simple example
here for this math problem.
And you could sample
the response many times.
For the first response,
you will get $18.
And for the second
one, you will get $26.
And again, you will get a $18.
And then we look at
the final answer.
And then choose the
most frequent one.
That's exactly the
process implementing
marginalization in probability.
We don't look at the
recent past, which
only shows the most frequent
answer, not the most
frequent reasoning paths.
That's the trick.
That's called
marginalization empirically.
And if you apply this approach,
you can see a huge improvement.
It's really surprising.
I know in the current
days, you may think, OK,
if we want to get
huge improvement,
you probably need to
spend a lot of time
to build a sophisticated
math formulations.
We don't have to.
So for GSM8K problems,
we can see that.
Even for fine-tuning GPT-3
models, they can actually 33%.
And then OpenAI used a
verifier to get actually 55%.
And with use PaLM model plus
CoT, we get accuracy 58%.
That's amazing.
That's a match the
performance from the verifier.
However, the most
surprising thing
is, after applying
self-consistency,
the accuracy jumped to 75%.
The relative improvement
is nearly 50%.
And use PaLM-3, we even
get an accuracy 92%
And of course, when
we say, OK, yeah,
that's for PaLM models, the
model for several years,
sounds 10 years ago,
because in the current days,
every year is just
like one decade.
The whole field
is moving so fast.
Actually, if you
look at o1 model--
I forgot when OpenAI released.
One month?
Probably October last year.
And actually they also showed
the results by aggregation.
See that consensus at 64 years.
And then we still see
a great improvement
by aggregation or
self-consistency.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] it seems
to be more expensive.
And they seem to
run more sources
at the expense of quality.
Yes, great point. of course.
Yes, use [INAUDIBLE]
sufficiency and using
more samples will be more
expensive, use more tokens.
And people see that kind
of inference-time scaling.
Yeah.
There are so many ways for
inference-time scaling.
If you use longer CoT, that
also increase inference time.
So actually, when
some people talk to me
about inference-time
scaling, really, I
don't know what they exactly
means, unless they can clearly
see what scaled.
Yeah.
And the self-consistency is
definitely a way to scale up.
Yeah.
And also self-consistency is
a naturally self-calibrated.
Higher consistency
indicates higher accuracy.
It's for GSM8K benchmark.
Actually, when the
consistency is more than 80%,
The accuracy is nearly 100%.
So I know some people care
about uncertainty or confidence
in prediction, and they
can just simply try
sampling multiple times.
And I have two questions here.
So to make sure everyone
got the really key ideas
in self-consistency, I
hope you know how to--
you really found a lot of
fun using this simple idea.
So the first question is say,
"When the LLM outputs a direct
answer without intermediate
steps, will you still
sample several times,
and then choose the
most common answer?"
Will you?
Does anyone have an answer here?
If the model just directly
generates an answer,
what do we do?
Yeah, go ahead.
This is like-- you can
just get the probabilities.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, exactly.
Exactly.
Just like exactly what we did in
the classical machine learning.
We have used logistic
regression to get a py given x.
We just need to maximize
the probability there.
That's why we couldn't
see self-consistency
in the old machine
learning literature.
It's unnecessary.
It's only useful
for LLM reasoning.
That's why we see it here.
After we have reasoning, and
then we need self-consistency.
Yeah.
And the second
question is, "Change
self-consistency by letting
LLM generate multiple response
instead of sampling
multiple times,
and then choosing the
most common answer.
Does this make sense?"
You can see [INAUDIBLE] model
generate five answers instead
of a sample [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
Actually, what I tried that.
And again, for
everything, we just
need to follow the machine
learning principle.
Actually, this principle is
called max marginal inference.
Yeah.
You just need to
choose the final answer
with the maximum probability.
That's all we need to know.
You don't have to think about
any fancy things about LLMs,
don't have to
compare with humans.
Max is all we need here.
And one can naturally--
of course, self-consistency
has a problem.
You see the unique answer.
You check the frequency
of the unique answer.
And for general problems,
it's hard to see.
the answer would
be a single token.
And for example,
for this problem,
you will see all the
answers are different.
In this case, we
have a contention
about self-consistency.
It's called a universal
self-consistency.
And for this problem
here, you can
see the second response
is the most common one--
Japan, China, and India, because
all these three countries
are in all other answers.
And we just need
to let LLMs choose
the most consistent response.
I've talked about how
to use aggregation
to improve reasoning.
And the other way
is about retrieval.
So I know there's a lot of
debate about everything you say.
People say, OK,
LLMs may not just
do retrieval instead
of reasoning.
I know many people--
I saw that debate
in social media.
And actually, to me, it's
always hard to differentiate
retrieval and reasoning.
And when I-- every
[INAUDIBLE] or senior area
chairs for all the
conference almost every year.
And we always have to talk
about the novelty of each paper.
And actually, it's
similar to the debate
is retrieval or reasoning?
Yeah?
So we have the concept
of self-consistence.
So try and experiment with
trying different models
to run in parallel and
then run in parallel.
They may have periodic running
or running concurrently
with running in Gemini 2.5 for
different models in parallel
for the same question, then at
the end just having a verifier.
So some about finding the
most consistent results.
Yes.
Yes, if you are generating
response from different models,
that will be more like
the model assembling
approach, because many models
and the combined results,
like a random forest, yes.
Yeah.
The mathematical
principle is not exactly
the same as self-consistency,
but the implementations
are the same.
Yes, yeah, great point.
And yeah, about--
actually again,
I'm not interested in the debate
about retrieval or reasoning.
And for people working--
actually, I work in industry.
I really just care
about performance.
So to me, just retrieval
plus reasoning.
Why I should do the debate?
Yeah.
So in 2024, we have a paper
about analogical reasoning.
So I can just use
this small example
to show why retrieval is
important in reasoning.
So for this problem,
see, what's the area
of the square with the
four vertices, blah, blah?
The highlighted text is added by
me and say, OK, it's a prompt.
Recall a related problem
and then solve this one.
So at that moment, I tried
GPT-3.5 and also our own model.
And they failed
solving this problem.
After adding the
prompt of recording
a related problems, and
the model can solve it.
Let's see what happened here.
After Toyota model two
vehicle-related problems.
And the model did find
a related problem.
Related problem doesn't
mean the same problem.
It's indeed just
a related problem.
You can see the
related problem here
is finding the
distance between two
points on a coordinate plane.
And this formula there,
and then the model.
Oh, yeah, now I know how
to compute the distance
and then how to
compute the area.
It's just a small case
to show how retrieval
is important in reasoning.
Here's another example
called a step back
for the physical problems.
And before solving this
problem, we just let a model--
we just give few short
examples to show the model, OK,
before solving this problem,
you can make a step back
to consider more abstract
problem, get the principle,
and then solve it.
That's how retrieval
works for reasoning.
And I think now everyone
knows deep research.
Deep research exactly
the same idea here.
So we have a Gemini
Deep Research and also
OpenAI Deep Research.
And one of OpenAI's Deep
Research lead was my intern.
And after his PhD,
and he joined OpenAI,
and he invented Deep Research.
Yeah.
And you see how
Deep Research works
because they can find a
similar problem or knowledge
to solve the problem.
Yeah, the basic
idea is very simple.
Now, I can give a summary here.
Actually, forget about this
debate for LLM reasoning or not.
For LLMs, reasoning is always
better than no reasoning,
and RL fine-tuning
is better than SFT.
Aggregating multiple answers
is better than one answer.
Of course, they
will be more costly.
And retrieval plus reasoning
is better than reasoning only.
And yeah, that's
the end of my talk.
And for the next
breakthroughs, I know you--
I really want to
see, OK, how to solve
the task beyond unique
verifiable answers
in the kind of days.
And I also want
to see how people
build real applications instead
of just solving benchmarks.
I think all benchmarks
will be saturated soon.
Yeah.
And what you guys are
very passionate about AGI
or build LLMs.
I would like to quote
Richard Feynman here.
"The truth always turns out to
be simpler than you thought."
And I think that's particularly
true for LLM research.
And I saw so many
academic papers,
always complicated many things.
So that's why I just keep my
talk as simple as possible.
Actually, it's indeed simple.
That's it.
Yeah, thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks, Danny, for the
very insightful as well as
interesting talk.
So now we'll be
taking questions.
We have some questions
online from Slido and Zoom,
but also in person.
So we can maybe start with
some in-person questions.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
So earlier on in the lecture,
you talked about confidence.
And a common way
to do this is just
taking the average
log probabilities
of output token sequences.
So my question is,
do you think there
are better ways to do this?
And also is this a good
indicator for hallucinations?
Oh, for a first slide, when I
talk about confidence just, not
aggregation, just the ability
for next token prediction,
just a conditional probability
for the generation.
Yeah.
You can just look at the
log props from the model
and you can see the probability.
Yeah.
And do you think this is a good
indicator for hallucinations?
Yeah.
I think so, yeah.
From our empirical
observation, yeah.
And we can see
after recent path,
there's a huge jump in
confidence for the final answer.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Well, earlier you mentioned
that, for example,
Richard Sutton said that it's
scaling, learning, and search.
And your opinion is more
like scaling and learning
is all you need.
I'd just like to
expand more on that
and why you believe that
search is not as necessary.
That's why I used that example.
So actually, I should
make it more concrete.
We build models.
You don't have to keep in mind.
But in the after model is
built and you can use search
as a tool, as a special
case of tool use,
like a train-of-thought
prompting,
they can just integrate
symbolic search with the model.
Yeah.
So part of a reasoning
research, I just
care about the
fundamental abilities.
Yeah.
For example, if you
to solve this problem,
the model could be motivated to
write a Python program to solve
those problems by search.
But for the reasoning process,
we don't need to search.
Just-- how to say it?
Of course, we can always
search everything.
That's why if you use a
search to solve any problems,
you can get a higher accuracy.
And I don't know.
That really depends
on what you want--
intelligence or just by search.
Yeah.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
You mentioned in the case
where there's no reasoning,
that it's not
necessary to sample
because you can simply
look at the logits.
But wouldn't sampling converge
on a different distribution
in the case, for example, where
the most likely next token leads
to a diffuse distribution
for the following token
and the different
paths spread out?
Whereas if you were to
sample a less likely token
were to lead to a
sharper distribution,
you could actually have a more
likely path of tokens there.
So wouldn't these two
methods fundamentally differ?
Good question.
Yeah, the problem is,
actually, we still
don't know how the distributions
are reshaped during the training
stage.
It's very unclear there.
Yeah.
So to me, it's very hard
to answer this question,
because we still don't
have good explanation
how the distribution reshaped
for the final distribution.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Hi, thank you for the talk.
So how do you differentiate
reasoning and answer?
Do you need to extract
that number from the tokens
from the final string,
the output string?
And what if the answer
can be a program?
Then how do you differentiate
the reasoning and the answer?
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, if the answer
is a program,
it will be harder to extract,
will be harder to subtract.
So when people use
a RL fine-tuning,
and that's why you just see--
I just took math problems,
so competitive programming
problems.
Yeah.
So I think for the general
case, for your case,
you have to write a very careful
parser for the final answer.
Yeah.
I see.
And also, what if the problem
is very challenging such that
actually the lower
confidence answer
might be the correct
answer because--
It's possible, yeah.
Then how can I use a
self-consistency method?
Self-consistency is not perfect.
It's perfect if it's done right.
Yeah, not perfect.
Thank you.
So considering that the
conversations that AGI
is coming from two to
five years from now, how--
and basically, if it's true,
then let's say 90% of jobs
are automated.
What skills do you
develop in kids
to give them a shot to survive
in the future that is coming?
That's a big question.
Who said AGI will
come in five years?
There's AI 2027 by Daniel
Kokotajlo, Lots of conversations
in the AI community that
given the timeline of two
to five years.
I was in-- last year
there was a workshop.
And I remember
one audience asked
me a question and the panelist.
And she said, OK, and AI
is moving so fast forward,
and what would be the most scary
thing in the next few years?
And yeah, I remember some people
did talk about the risk of AI.
but my answer is to
me, most scary thing
is AI winter comes back,
and then I lost my job.
Actually, I saw
many restrictions
for the current approach.
I know many people like the
chat bots, LLM sort of things.
I actually, really want to
see real killer applications
from the kind of AI research.
I don't know if anyone
really needs those AI stuff
or not, or just for fun.
Yeah.
I'm not quite sure about that.
I know actually the AI models
is really good for programming.
Yeah, it can be a good
assistant for coding.
And that's all I know about it.
Yeah.
We should be fine.
I think we're out of time.
But thanks, everybody,
for a great questions.
And thanks again to
Danny for the great talk.
[APPLAUSE]